Guide to the George Aptecker Collection CBHM.0003
Center for Brooklyn History
George Aptecker Collection
circa 1898-2019
1952-1990
Center for Brooklyn History
Aptecker, George, 1931-2018
CBHM.0003
31.3 Linear Feet in 5 record cartons, 4 document boxes, and 21 oversize flat boxes.
Materials documenting the life and work of photographer George Aptecker (1931-2018). The bulk of the collection includes black-and-white negatives and prints showing New York City street scenes and portraits. Other items include journals, exhibit information, personal items, and materials concerning Aptecker's books, Beyond Despair and Passing Through.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated by Andrea Aptecker in 2021.
Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in six series:
Series I: Writing is arranged by format, with items arranged chronologically.
Series II: Personal and Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Correspondence is grouped in folders 1-6, all other items are housed in folders 7-12 with a separate chronological arrangement.
Series III: Exhibits and Ephemera is arranged chronologically.
Series IV: Photograph Collecting and Dealing is arranged chronologically.
Series V: Books is arranged by title.
Series VI: Photographs is arranged in four sub-series by format. Items in each sub-series maintain the original order and numbering system imposed by George Aptecker. Box and binder numbers assigned and arranged by the Archivist.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials documenting the life and work of photographer George Aptecker. The bulk of the collection includes photographic negatives and prints created between 1952 and 1990. All film is 35mm or medium format black-and-white, with most negative sheets paired with a corresponding contact sheet print. Aptecker's numbering system has been maintained to label negative sleeves, although numbers are not consistent. Numbers appear out of order, numbers are often duplicated, and some sheets were left unnumbered. Most negatives were not dated or titled.
Subjects include photographs of Aptecker's honeymoon in Europe, portraits of friends and family, classrooms, boxers, and museum visitors. Street scenes show Manhattan, Brooklyn, and presumably the Bronx, as well as the Coney Island beach and boardwalk. Also included are negatives and prints for Aptecker's books, Beyond Despair and Passing Through. Most prints were created from negatives in sub-series I and are black-and-white, although some have been hand colored.
Also included in this collection is Aptecker's journals, dating 1955-2014. Entries vary in length, covering day-to-day observations, poems, photography notes, relationships with friends and family, and general musings. His journal concerning Beyond Despair is housed with the Books series. Other items in the Books series include promotional materials, original layouts, reviews, and copies of Beyond Despair. Also included is notes and layouts for Passing Through, which was not published. Items in the Exhibits and Ephemera series cover promotional materials and reviews for Aptecker's photography exhibits. This series also includes a scrapbook created by Aptecker containing clippings, correspondence, and copies of articles he contributed to U.S. Camera magazine. Drafts of these articles can be found in the Writing series.
Correspondence is personal and professional; correspondence concerning Beyond Despair is housed with the Books series. Personal items include certificates, family photographs, and a USB containging a copy of In the Darkroom, a short film about the life of George Aptecker created by his daughter, Andrea Aptecker. Items in the Photograph Collecting and Dealing series concern Aptecker's side business as a fine art photography dealer. Photographer contracts, biographies, notes, and clippings concerning the collecting market are included.
Prior to donation, Andrea Aptecker included notes with some items to provide context. These notes have not been removed.
Related Materials
Irving I. Herzberg photograph collection, BCMS.0056
Jamel Shabazz photograph collection, BCMS.0055
John D. Morrell Photograph Collection, ARC.005
Larry Racioppo Collection, BCMS.0053
Lucille Fornasieri-Gold photographs, 2008.013
Biographical Note
George Aptecker was born on March 5, 1931 in the Bronx to Moses and Diana Aptecker. He graduated from James Monroe High School in June 1949, working in a pillow factory before joining the United States Army in October 1951. While overseas, Aptecker had the opportunity to travel in Germany, France and Spain, photographing street scenes, portraits, and bull fights. After returning to New York, he purchased a new camera and enrolled in the New York Institute of Photography. In 1955 he began journaling, a habit he would maintain for the rest of his life.
In 1957 Aptecker married Sandra "Sandie" Bender; their daughter Diana was born in 1964 followed by Andrea "Annie" born in 1968. During this time he wrote and contributed articles to U.S. Camera Magazine, Camera 35 Magazine, and Modern Photography Magazine. He also exhibited his work at the Village Camera Club, Underground Gallery, and the Metropolitan Museum of Art. His photographs appeared in print for the New York Times and N.Y World Telegram. The family purchased a house in Brooklyn, but Aptecker was soon unemployed and looking for work. In 1973 he began driving a New York City taxi, recording his experiences in his photography work and journals. He then began work as a night watchman at the Metropolitan Museum of Art while maintaining a small business collecting and dealing fine art photography. The family moved to New Jersey in 1975.
Aptecker's book, Beyond Despair, a collection of symbolic photographs and quotes about the holocaust was published in 1980 with a forward by Elie Wiesel. Aptecker's second book, Passing Through, was not published. He continued to exhibit his work in New York City and New Jersey, and in 1981 was named Director of Development for the Jewish Reconstructionist Foundation. Aptecker and Sandy divorced in 1984. In the 1990s Aptecker's eyesight began to deteriorate and he stopped making photographs. He died on June 3, 2018 at the age of 87. His work is in the permanent collections of the Museum of Modern Art, the Brooklyn Museum, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, and several private collections.
Portrait photography; Coney Island (New York, N.Y.); Black-and-white prints (photographs); Journals (accounts); Diaries; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Museums; Taxicab drivers -- New York (State) -- New York; Photography—Exhibitions; Negatives (photographic); Tourism |z Europe; Catskill Mountains (N.Y.); Manhattan (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I: Writing
  - Journal, 1955-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Journal, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Journal, 1964-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Journal Pages and Notes, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Loose Journal Pages (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Loose Journal Pages, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Journals, 1972-1973, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Journals, 1974-1975, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Journals, 1993-1996, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Journals, 1998-2001 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Journals, 2001-2002, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Journals, 2010-2014, 2012-2014 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Camera Article Drafts, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Poetry and Short Story, circa 1970, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photography Notes, circa 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series II: Personal and Correspondence
  - Aptecker, Diana, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bearded Man and Nude Painting Correspondence, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Aptecker, Sandy, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photography Opprotunities, 1962-1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Aptecker, Moses, 1966-1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Aptecker, Andrea, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Family Photographs, circa 1890, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Birth Certificate, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Military Service Records, 1953, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Village Camera Club Certificate, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - High School Graduation Certification, issued 1967 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Short Film on USB, 2021 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Series III: Exhibits and Ephemera
  - Photography Exhibits, Promotional, circa 1960-1979 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, 1960-1982 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook, 1960-2002, bulk 1960-1980 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Invoices, 1961-1971 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Notes, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Series IV: Photograph Collecting and Dealing
  - Business Cards, circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Clippings and Notes, 1971-1981 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - George Aptecker Biography, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Model Release Form, circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Photographer Biographies, circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Photographer Agreements, 1983-1987 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Series V: Books
  - Beyond Despair, Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Beyond Despair, Journal, circa 1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Beyond Despair, Order Forms and Mailers, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Beyond Despair, Page Layouts, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Beyond Despair, Printing Invoice, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Beyond Despair, Photocopies, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Beyond Despair, Promotional, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Beyond Despair, Reception Invitation, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Beyond Despair, Reviews and Clippings, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Beyond Despair, Books, 1980 (Box 5, Item 1-6)
  - Beyond Despair, Page Layouts, circa 1980 (Box 30)
  - Passing Through, Notes, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Passing Through, Photocopies, circa 1997 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Passing Through, Layout, circa 1997 (Box 4, Item 1)
- Series VI: Photographs
  - Sub-Series I: Negatives and Contact Sheets
    - Images 1-319: Museum, Portraits, Coney Island, Street Scenes, Swimming, Daycare (Box 6, Binder 1)
    - Images 161-223: Dance/Movement Class, Beach, Restaurant, Portraits, Museum (Box 6, Binder 2)
    - Images 224-276: Museum, Portraits, Art class (Box 6, Binder 3)
    - Images 278-329: Coney Island, Portraits, Street Scenes, Classroom (Box 6, Binder 4)
    - Images 330-400: Ping-Pong, Street Scenes, Portraits, Boxing (Box 6, Binder 5)
    - Images 417-640: Street Scenes, Portraits, Beach, Kids, Marching Band (Box 6, Binder 6)
    - Images 321-530: Ping-Pong, Portraits, Boxing, Street Scene, Wedding, Beach, Dolls (Box 7, Binder 7)
    - Images 45-1049: Portraits, mannequins, Houses, Street Scenes, Dolls, Beach, Museum (Box 7, Binder 8)
    - Images 411-481: Street Scenes, Portraits, Theater Rehearsal, Boxing, Coney Island, Museum (Box 7, Binder 9)
    - Images 949-1068, unnumbered: Beach, Portraits, Museum, Masks, Woods, Chess, Mannequins, Israel, Catskills (Box 7, Binder 10)
    - Images 23-1059: Freehold, Masks, Street Scenes, Mannequins, Catskills, Cemetery, Boxing (Box 7, Binder 11)
    - Images 1012-1132, GA 4-GA31: Masks, Catskills, Snow, Cemetery, Trees, Sun Ranch, Beach, Portraits (Box 7, Binder 12)
    - Images 9-32200, 1A: Museum, Street Scene, Boxing, Europe, Masks, Coney Island, Synagogue, Portraits, Hand Written Notes (Box 8, Binder 13)
    - Images 15-1124, GA7-GA29: Europe, Catskills, Dolls, Street Scenes, Museum, Masks (Box 8, Binder 14)
    - Images 14-1129, GA8-GA19: Playground, Street Scenes, Brighton Beach, Signs, Classroom, Portraits, Museum (Box 8, Binder 15)
    - Images 4-54, mostly unnumbered: Portrait, Street Scenes, Beach, Portrait, Dancers, Europe (Box 8, Binder 16)
    - Images unnumbered: Portrait, Family, Street Scenes, Theater Rehearsal, Europe (Box 8, Binder 17)
    - Images unnumbered: Europe, Portraits, Synagogue (Box 8, Binder 18)
    - Images 5-77, mostly unnumbered: Portraits, Street Scenes (Box 9, Binder 19)
  - Sub-Series II: Prints: 8x10 and Smaller
    - Portraits, Masks, Dolls, Cars (Box 9, Binder 20)
    - Hand Painted, Portraits, Museum, Mannequins (Box 9, Binder 21)
    - Museum, Masks, Mannequins, Dolls, Gam-anon 12 Steps Pamphlet (Box 9, Binder 22)
    - Masks, Museum, Portraits, School, Mannequins (Box 10, Binder 23)
    - Portraits, Masks, Animals, Mannequins (Box 10, Binder 24)
    - Portraits, Dolls, Bullfighting, Handwritten Notes (Box 10, Binder 25)
  - Sub-Series III: Prints: 11x14
    General
    Includes some smaller prints.
    - Mannequins, Masks, Portraits, Shadows (Box 11)
    - Mannequins, Portraits, Street Scenes, Collage (Box 12)
    - Portraits, Collage, Street Scenes (Box 13)
    - Street Scenes, Portraits, Beach, Bullfighting (Box 14)
    - Portraits, Mannequins, Collage, Masks, Family, Museum (Box 15)
    - Portraits, Museum, Collage, Mannequins (Box 16)
    - Collage, Portraits (Box 17)
    - Beyond Despair (Box 18)
    - Beyond Despair (Box 19)
    - Beyond Despair, Statues, Masks, Portraits (Box 20)
    - Passing Through Images, Portraits, Masks (Box 21)
    - Paintings, Trinity Church, Collages, Portraits (Box 22)
    - Portraits, Objects (Box 23)
    - Street Scenes, Boxing, Portraits, Hand Painted (Box 24)
    - Portraits, Street Scenes, Museum (Box 25)
  - Sub-Series IV: Prints: 16x20
    - Mannequins, Portraits, Collages, Drawings, Paintings (Box 26)
    - Portraits, Masks, Collages, Dolls (Box 27)
    - Boxing, Portraits, Street Scenes (Box 28)
    - Portraits, Collages (Box 29)